This is why now, you're going to get me
started now here.
We need to operate utterly independently
of the Israelis. I've said a million
times, I'm going to repeat it.
Starting in the mid-1980s when Ronald
Reagan was president, every single
Israeli prime minister, no matter who it
was, when they came to the United States
and they come all the time, they would
say, "Please attack Iran. Please attack
Iran. Please attack Iran." And every
single president said, "I'm not going to
do it."
Obama said, what, 2 weeks ago, that
Netanyahu came and said, "If you don't
attack Iran, we're going to use nuclear
weapons." And Obama said, "Go ahead.
Go ahead, use them."
He called the bluff and they didn't use
them. Since 1986,
the Iranians have been 6 months away
from a nuclear weapon. Well, guess what?
No, they're not. That's a lie.
There've been two, count them, two
national intelligence estimates. What a
national intelligence estimate is is
it's a sense of the community of the
intelligence community, formal paper.
And this is important. If the CIA writes
a paper, uh, okay, congratulations. This
is the CIA believes this or DIA believes
that or State Department believes this
other thing.
An NIE, national intelligence estimate,
is you have all 18 intelligence agencies
sitting around a giant table
in the offices of the National
Intelligence Council
and they're going sentence by sentence.
Okay, the first sentence is and the the
National Intelligence Officer reads it.
"Anybody have any objections?" And all
18 people get to weigh in. It takes
weeks normally to coordinate a paper
like this.
All 18 intelligence agencies concluded
decisively twice that the Iranians did
not have a nuclear weapons program. How
recent were these? The first one was
and the other one was like 2009,
something like that. And in addition,
Ayatollah Khamenei issued a fatwa saying
that it was a sin to develop a nuclear
weapon, and that's why they were not
enriching to weapons-grade
levels.
>> Yeah.
>> And the Israelis said they didn't give a
[__] They want us to bomb, bomb, bomb.
So then finally we did.
>> The meeting that you're talking about,
where they're First off, I'm surprised
that any You fill a room with 18
different agencies, I'm actually
surprised anything ever in the world
gets accomplished.
>> when I tell you I'd never hated anything
in my entire career as much as
coordinating an NIE. I was the Deputy
National Intelligence Officer for a
while.
Um, and then
to get promoted to GS-14,
I had to write an NIE. So I wrote this
NIE in 19
97,
and it was called Iraq
Saddam's Next 12 Months.
And we coordinated it in 8 hours.
And the National Intelligence Officer,
Ben Bonk, God rest his soul, terrific
guy, he came to me afterwards and he
said, "That was the fastest coordination
session for an NIE that I've seen in 25
years." And I said, "This one was
actually pretty easy, Ben. Saddam could
threaten Kuwait. Saddam could threaten
the Kurds. Saddam could threaten the
Shiites. Saddam will probably try to
violate sanctions."
>> Yeah.
>> Big deal.
>> So are those NIEs,
in layman's terms, are they a way to
assess
risk and then you can brief the policy
makers?
>> exactly what they're for.
>> And so the reason I asked this is it's
listening to Tulsi Gabbard
testify,
>> Mhm.
>> and she said
essentially, I'm paraphrasing, Michael,
if you could pull it up, that Trump is
the
single or sole individual that
determines the immediacy of the threat.
>> Mhm.
>> I feel like that premise is incredibly
dangerous.
>> It is dangerous. But
>> And I also don't know is that is that a
real assessment? Because wouldn't an
organization
or organizations create something like
an NIE and he would be able to
I'm assuming that that is the role of
intelligence organizations. And and and
maybe this is a gross misunderstanding
of what she was saying.
But if that's the case, what if one day
after we're done with Iran he goes
Mexico is an imminent threat. Like
is it really
like that? Like the guy sitting in the
chair with the Diet Coke button gets to
just determine it like that?
>> This
The The The answer to the question is
very complicated. So the CIA, really any
intelligence service, no I should say
the individual authorized to determine
what constitutes an imminent threat. I
thought that that was the role of the
intelligence apparatus.
>> So
the CIA, really any intelligence
service, I should say
>> So the individual authorized to
determine what constitutes an imminent
threat. I thought that that was the role
of the intelligence apparatus.
>> The intelligence apparatus will say
the intelligence community does not
believe that Iran is an imminent threat.
The president can elect to ignore that.
So technically, sure, he's the decision
maker, he's the one that's going to make
the final call.
Any other president in modern American
history
has been surrounded by, you know, the
best and the brightest. And this guy was
a professor to Harvard and this guy was
the deputy assistant secretary of
whatever and this guy, you know,
whatever. You you surround yourself with
people who know these things. The Henry
Kissingers of their day. Although I hate
to use that example, but you know what I
mean.
Um
So technically, the president is the
final authority on these issues. But any
other president will ask the Secretary
of State, "What do you think?" Secretary
of Defense, "What do you think?"
National Security Adviser, "What do you
think?" CIA Director, "What do you
think?" And everybody's going to weigh
in. And then [clears throat]
these are his top people. He's going to
in concert with them come to a policy
decision. Collaborative effort.
Collaborative effort. And remember that
the CIA is not a policy organization. It
is a policy support organization.
George W. Bush did something that was
very, very controversial just as I was
leaving the agency. In the president's
daily brief, which is, you know, six
days a week, 16 pages,
the first article is a full page. After
that, there are a couple of articles of
a paragraph of fact and a paragraph of
analysis.
Um
he ordered the CIA
to put a paragraph of fact, a paragraph
of analysis, and a paragraph entitled
policy recommendation.
Well, that flies in the face of
everything that the CIA is.
You're supposed to be
the one that makes the policy, not the
CIA. The CIA can tell you what the facts
are and what the facts likely mean, but
then you make a decision. That only
lasted for George W. Bush's second term.
And then it went back to its normal
state of equilibrium.
My point being
sure.
Donald Trump is the last person. But
then, Trump told 60 Minutes not most in
the most most recent interview, the one
before, when asked
"Who are your closest advisers?"
He said, "I don't have any. I just go
with my gut."
And we've not had a president like that
before.
>> That is a bold mission statement. Yeah.
>> It is. It's very, very bold, very gutsy.
Yeah.
>> Another thing I'd like to see
>> Do you Do you mind searching to see when
those NIEs were
NIE on Iran the Iran nuclear program?
>> I'll tell you what I would like to have
looked at very deeply, perhaps
rewritten, is the authorized use of
military force.
>> That's a tall order.
>> It's a tall order?
>> here again, you've got these cowards
>> and bent by every president since its
inception?
>> Yes, and you've got these cowards on
Capitol Hill.
>> We got 2007
>> 2007 and 2003. I thought it was 3 and 9.
3 and 7.
>> Yeah, the AUMF provides
some immense latitude.
It's uh
Sometimes I'll get online and people
think I'm arguing or What was the term
somebody used? They called me pedantic.
So I had to look that one up. I had to
look that one up. Cuz they're like,
"We're at war." I'm like, "No, we're
not."
>> No, we're not.
>> And and the point is isn't that [__]
ridiculous?
>> Yes.
>> That we can do this.
They What they think is again, I had to
look up the word pedantic and now I try
to use it every day cuz it's really
good. But [laughter]
somebody called me mercurial the other
day.
>> That's a good one, too.
>> I had to look it up.
>> Yeah.
>> But it's it baffles me
that we can do every action that looks
exactly like warfare.
>> Yeah.
>> But not as a country declared as war.
And
>> [clears throat]
>> again, it's it's a way where actions can
be taken without the oversight that I
want to see in place.
>> But and then people are like, "Oh, it's
a political issue." I'm like, "Guess
what? Your team captain
did the He bent the [__] out of this,
too."
>> That's right.
>> Blue and red. They manipulated the [__]
out of this.
>> have not declared war on on anybody
since Vietnam.
No, we never declared war
>> No, I'm sorry, but since before Vietnam.
>> Yeah, yeah. It was World War II.
>> Yeah.
>> On December 8th, we declared war on
Japan and the next day we declared war
on Germany.
And that's it. That was the last time.
Even Korea wasn't a war. It was a police
action.
>> What do you think it would take to
change that thing? I don't think Well,
first of all, I don't think people
realize the powers that it provides and
the
off-ramp at least in the short term to
oversight that our foundational
documents were written upon.
>> Mhm. Why would we want that?
>> I know, right? The Constitution is so
crystal clear on these issues. It It
makes
the executive, the legislative, and the
judicial branches of government co-equal
branches. Co-equal. And then you have
these clowns like Lindsey Graham saying,
"I want to make Congress weaker."
It's like, are you out of your mind?
>> An argument could be made. Yes.
>> [laughter]
>> There's a lot of stuff that we could say
about Lindsey Graham.
>> For clarity, an argument could be made
about as well on that. It's you know,
you know, [laughter]
>> Strong arguments and weaker arguments,
but
I don't Yeah. I And people
>> National security.
>> Mhm.
>> Safety.
>> What's the saying? Somebody willing to
sacrifice liberty for security is
>> is it
>> Yeah.
>> worthy deserves neither.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> I've never seen the government give the
power back.
>> No.
>> Ever. Ever. It We have to come to some
catastrophe
like that which resulted in the in the
uh Church Committee before there's any
real change, like structural change.
>> Yeah.
And then is the system
so far
outgrown or so far outside of the lines
that they're supposed to color in,
could it even be put back in or
reoriented back in? I don't know the
answer to that.
>> You know, it's different now, too, than
it was in 1975 just because of the state
of technology. Like the How do you put
that genie back in the bottle?
>> I love the shorts of you on the Diary of
the CEO just blowing people's minds with
what the agency can do.
>> I mean, Vault 7.
>> God.
>> All of that's public. How is it that
nobody paid any attention to that? It's
all public.
>> think that they're doing it to our
enemies.
>> Yeah.
>> And then the reality is that's not true.
>> No.
They can do it to all of us.
>> How do I Okay.
How does somebody survive in an
electronic world? Like what How does
>> You know, we got to all turn into Ted
Kaczynski. Is what it [laughter] is what
it comes down to. You live in a shack in
Idaho.
>> Yeah, no, I think it was Montana.
>> Montana.
>> Yeah. Somebody bought his shack. They
have it I think as their like lawnmower
storage.
>> Oh my god. Can you imagine?
>> Yeah, I can't get behind the bombing
campaign, but under like going on like a
little tech break, I totally understand.
>> Yeah, I get it. But even then, in a
world where everybody is defined by
their technological usage, just like my
wife doing accidental SDRs, you might
end up on their radar because like this
guy has got some amazing fieldcraft.
He's a ghost. Like no, he just hates
>> Yeah, [laughter] he's a Luddite. That
That's all. He's a Luddite.
>> Uh but I mean
how do
how do you operate in a world where they
can reach into basically anything
that is powered
>> Mhm.
>> and take it over remotely? I mean, is it
just forced acceptance? I mean, it's not
like you and I can stop it. You can tell
as many people that it has happened as
possible.
>> on my cell phone right now, and I know
you are, too.
>> and NSA is with us, right? Hello, NSA. I
You guys should get a budget increase.
Good job.
>> Yeah, I there are a couple of little
things that I've done.
Like uh
you know, Tucker Carlson's got this uh
or he advertises this uh
cell phone like encrypted cell phone.
>> Yeah, but I could point you back to the
agency making a cell phone for the
specific usage of invading drug cartels.
>> [laughter]
>> I don't have I don't have one of these
cell phones. You're exactly right. I
don't want to have have a cell phones,
but it got me to thinking.
And so, um
I went I
I went to an electronic store
in Europe, and I just bought a cell
phone, and I was able to register it in
in
another name. And I have a spare SIM
card. I can pop out my SIM card, pop
this one in, and this is registered in a
Middle Eastern country. So, wherever I
happen to be, I'll just go into the
local version of Radio Shack or or Best
Buy or whatever.
>> Yeah.
>> And I'll buy a I'll buy a burner phone
or I'll buy a SIM card and swap them
out.
But even that's not going to
>> Yeah.
>> really protect me in the long run.
>> give you
that'd give you a little bit of a head
start.
>> Mhm.
>> They're going to find you.
>> A little bit. Oh, they'll find you.
>> Yeah, yeah. Especially with the
computing power.
>> That that's another one like I mean 25
years ago that's how we got I was a
beta.
>> Yeah.
>> He he made one single mistake. He he
accessed his emails with a landline.
>> That was it.
>> I was killing people because of their
SIM cards.
>> See?
>> 2005.
>> Mhm.
>> I mean
>> They learned though. They learned quick.
>> Yeah, they did.
>> And we adapted, but yeah, it's you know,
these
NSA databases and and just data farms
that are showing up in
odd locations and he's like,
"Every single electric like we're not
looking through it though. We're just
storing it."
>> Right. Yeah, you're not looking through
it.
>> Right now.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, then why do you need this gigantic
facility in Utah that you've built?
>> Because we might need to look at it
later.
>> Yeah.
>> And then
depending on who's throwing the
>> Without a warrant, by the way.
>> That's the biggest thing that bugs me.
That I
Either the Constitution matters or it
doesn't. Either it means something to be
an American and I truly still believe
that we can be a beacon to the world.
But we don't do that by hiding our
missteps. We have to be honest about
where we have fallen short and we have
to learn from our mistakes.
>> Mhm.
>> And that last one right there, I'm not
so sure that we're actually doing.
>> I have to agree.
I have to agree.
>> It's like we reinvent the wheel every
time we elect a new president.
Yeah, and that's where I landed. I don't
think this is a top-down fix. I think
it's a bottom-up fix. It's going to be
generational.
>> Mhm.
>> And and I I have three children. I have
a my daughter I'm getting ready to get
into birthday season, so I'll have 18,
21, and 23.
>> Wonderful.
>> They're fantastic.
I'm loving their skepticism.
>> And good.
>> Yeah, it's it's healthy. I don't I don't
like throw fire on it and like fashion
them like uh tin foil berets or anything
like that. But I I like it. Michael's an
example, too. I mean, he's 23 years old.
He's, you know, his views of the world
and the way he thinks about things and
his response to what he is seeing being
put out nationally and globally, I ask
him about it all the time. Because he
also has a different optic than you and
I have had based off of our previous
careers and
the answers are very informative. The
pendulum
I don't know if we have like bounced off
of where it's swinging to, but it is
going to come back.
>> It has to.
>> And I think the country will survive.
I'm not saying a tire or two might not
go off the track, but
>> Right.
>> [laughter]
>> I think we're going to be okay.
>> Right.
>> Because of what I see from the younger
generation.
>> Good.
>> I'm hopeful.
>> I am, too.
>> Maybe I'm being
too incredibly optimistic. Dude, on that
note, I mean, there's such a difference
between
the price and the cost.
I mean, when you signed up to serve at
the agency, you paid that price. And
it's the same thing as military service.
You know how long you're going to enlist
for and you know that there's a risk
associated with that.
The cost though
is everything you can never calculate.
The strain on family, the the time away.
How has everything that has happened to
you like
and I'm sure it's changed over time, but
like with your children,
how how did it impact them or your
relationship with them?
>> It was devastating.
>> Yeah.
>> I have five children. I have four boys
and a girl. Boy, boy, boy, girl, boy.
Um four of them don't speak to me.
>> Still to this day? Mhm.
>> One I'm very close to. We speak almost
every day.
Um and then
>> started at the time where you uh I mean
>> Yeah, I was still in.
>> Well, and the reason I I mean, you have
talked on so many large platforms about
a lot of the things that you did in the
agency, so I'd rather just talk to you
as a person. You know what I mean? And
so people can go and
go watch Diary of a CEO. Just watch it.
When you talked to him about how they
can turn the speaker on a TV into a
microphone, I'm like, "Oh, yeah, they
definitely can do that." And he's just
like,
>> [laughter]
>> "What?" I'm like, "Yeah, dude, they got
you."
I thought everybody knew that. You and I
knew that. A lot of people don't want to
believe they have those abilities. So,
people can go reference that, but
you know, to me, I had a time period
when I was going through my divorce
where I lost 18 months with my oldest
son.
Very close now. I think our relationship
is better.
Well, and I hope that that can be the
case for you with your other kids.
>> I'm optimistic.
>> Did the relationship break when things
started becoming public about what had
happened with you at the agency? Yes.
>> God damn.
>> Yes.
Yeah.
>> I'll get there.
I'm optimistic. People often accuse me
of being
irrationally optimistic, overly
optimistic, but I prefer to live my life
like that. And I'm I'm hopeful and
relatively confident that things are
going to work out.
>> How old are they?
>> Uh
33, 30,
21, 19, and 14.
>> I think sometimes
they have to get their own laps around
the sun.
It's uh
>> Agreed.
>> I know there are
I understand
yet don't agree with
the criticism of what you did by coming
forward. I understand the people that
say that. In my opinion, I wish there
were more people who were like you who
were serving in the agency.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Because I saw it firsthand, you know,
and we were oftentimes the action arm of
the intelligence in air quotes.
>> Very much so.
>> And
>> You were.
it's not perfect and everybody's doing
the best that they can, but to me it's
it's a rare thing to be issued the flag
of your country and not rent it, you
know, or go buy it on a t-shirt, which
everybody can do what they want to, but
it has to mean something to me.
And and I from people on the outside
they can criticize what you did because
they don't have an understanding of it
and more importantly they don't have a
skin in the game.
>> No, they don't. And you know, I say I'm
not I'm not trying to [__] on people,
but
any slob can roll out of bed and write a
nasty comment on a YouTube page.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I I try hard just to ignore all that
noise. Remember this, Joe has said this
many times.
>> He's never encountered somebody in life
who is living an enriching
successful, joy-filled life
that spends their time being an [__]
on the internet.
>> Uh that's that's great.
>> I mean
>> I like that.
>> It really helps you recenter.
>> Yeah.
>> And often times now, I will respond to
people
and just say, "Listen, I don't know
what's going on in your life, but I
truly hope that whatever it is that
you're dealing with
gets better.
Because people who are doing well, they
don't act like this. Most of the time
you'll get a middle finger, a motorcon.
>> [laughter]
>> But I hope that it
I hope that it sticks with them and it
goes to the point
>> Yeah.
>> about the kids
more laps and more context.
It's if you can keep showing them who
you are,
I think you're going to be okay.
>> you're right. And and I'm very hopeful
in that respect, and I've I've also
made very clear to every one of them
that I'm a phone call away.
>> Mhm.
>> That's all they have to do.
>> I did the same thing with my son, too.
And one day the phone rang. And it
changed everything.
>> That's that's what I'm hoping for.
>> That 18 months felt like about 18
decades.
>> Yes.
>> For clarity.
>> Um
and it was it was all tied around that
time period of that divorce, but and I
get it, he was the oldest, probably the
most impacted by it, had a bad
processing ability that probably let him
go down in just a mental rabbit holes of
the whys and the hows, that's just the
five Ws, you know?
>> Mhm.
>> Um
Good.
>> I'm glad that happened for for both of
you.
>> All you can do, and the only thing I
could do, was consistently
be the best version of try to be the man
that I wanted to be, which I still fall
short every day.
But to show
>> Me, too.
>> that example,
>> Mhm.
>> they'll come back around, man.
They'll come back around.
>> God willing.
I'm hopeful.
>> Families are a bastard.
>> You know, I wonder, too,
if
if it's something about this generation
specifically. I've I've tried to do as
much reading about family estrangement
as I can. There are a lot of really good
books out there right now.
>> It's a really common issue, actually.
>> And that's exactly what I was going to
say. I I saw something on the news just
yesterday
saying that
25% of all American families are
experiencing some level or form of
family estrangement.
And it's easy to think you're alone. I
have a I have a friend. She used to
write to me when I was in prison. She
was a Broadway star from the '60s.
And now she's
almost 90 years old, and we call each
other every few weeks.
Her son, she has one child, her son,
who's now well into his 50s,
just cut her off.
Like 10 years ago, 12 years ago now.
Just cold turkey cut her off.
>> Mhm.
>> She doesn't have any idea why. She
called me one day, and she asked me if I
knew of a good private investigator. I
said, "Oh, yeah. I know a very good
private investigator." And I connected
them.
And she hired him. I didn't ask her why
she wanted him. It was her business. But
he told me all she wanted was a picture
of her granddaughter. Mhm. She had never
met her granddaughter.
And so he kind of, you know,
he parked across the street from the
school,
and um
and figured out who her granddaughter
was and took a picture.
But not a, you know, a minute goes by
that she's not thinking about
>> Yeah.
>> the son that she doesn't understand how
she lost or why she lost, and the
granddaughter that she's never met. She
doesn't have very much more time left on
on Earth.
>> Part of the harder realization is in
that, too, is that the situation may not
change. It may never change.
>> suspect
>> it hasn't by now. Her husband died, the
guy's father, and
and the guy never reacted or responded
in any way.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
Yeah, it's a it's a real shame, but it's
not uncommon is the point I wanted to
make. It's not uncommon. So, I hope for
the best.
>> Yeah.
So, my advice I'm not I'm not somebody
to give advice, but it's the only advice
I can give based on my own experience is
just keep being you. I'm glad that it
worked out for you.
It doesn't work out for everybody, for
sure. But that [clears throat] was you
want to talk about a humbling experience
that makes you question who you are as a
human being.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah, people think BUD/S is hard. I'm
like, "So, here's what you want to do.
You want to be tougher than a SEAL?
Go through a contentious divorce."
>> Right.
>> [laughter]
>> Seriously. Oh my god.
>> Like, stop researching these selection
courses to go through. Just get a
divorce. It's way harder.
Not actual advice that I'm giving to
anybody. This is completely sarcasm and
tongue-in-cheek, but
God, it will destroy you. It's truly the
hardest thing I've ever done, though.
>> Oh my god, me too. Yeah. I wouldn't wish
it on my worst enemy.
>> I would agree with that. I would agree
with that. It's
a man. There's not a the hard drive long
enough or big enough to encapsulate my
thoughts on that process, but
>> And I'll tell you another thing, Andy,
is you know, when you go some through
something like this,
you really get to see who your friends
are.
>> Yes.
>> Including people that you share blood
with, you know? Including people that
you may be married to or otherwise, you
know,
engaged to in some way. I had I had one
I have one cousin.
He's
he's a good 10 years older than I am.
And when I was a little kid, I always
looked up to him. He was like, you know,
the the big kid, good-looking, Navy
pilot.
And um
when I got arrested,
uh he called me and he said, "Listen, I
got to cut you off." I was like, "What?
What are you talking about?" He said,
"You brought shame to our family."
And I said,
"You think I didn't read about you in
the Washington Post that you were the
mayor of Alexandria, Virginia's coke
dealer?
You think I didn't know that you and
your guys are standing on the beach in
Florida waiting for the Colombians to
drop the bales of of of weed out of the
plane? I know all about you. And I
brought shame to our family? I said,
[__] you."
And I've cut him off. Well, now he's
like sending me Facebook friend
requests. "Hey cuz, you're really famous
now." Yeah, [__] you. I haven't
forgotten about 2012.
>> Yeah.
>> [__]
>> I have shifted years ago. Family
actually to me is nothing to do with
DNA.
It's how they treat you.
>> You got that right.
>> Plus, if you go deep enough and people
are like, "Oh, our family's perfect."
I'm like, "Tell me about your
grandparents."
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> in every family they're like, "Ooh, we
don't really talk about Uncle Bob that
much cuz he's [__] crazy." I'm like,
"We all got crazy."
>> I had an uncle like that, my
grandmother's brother. I I remember
meeting him. I must have been like 12
the first time I met him and I was like,
"How come I never heard of Uncle Bill?"
Like I said this to my mother, "How come
How come I never heard of Uncle Bill?
How is he my uncle?" "Oh, he's your
grandmother's brother." "How come I've
never met him? He lives here in the same
town. How come I never met him?" And she
said, "When you get a little older, I'll
explain it to you." Well, I'm like 15
and she finally explains to me, he he
was one of the American soldiers who
liberated Dachau concentration camp at
the end of the Second World War and it
made him nuts.
>> I see how it could.
>> So, yeah, seriously. So, he came back
with what today we know as PTSD. Back
then they called it shell shock and all
different kinds of things.
In 1953,
he had been home for 8 years.
He somehow got it into his head
that Richard Nixon, who had just been
uh elected vice president,
promised him a job at the post office in
Steubenville, Ohio.
>> Sounds reasonable.
>> Yeah.
So, he puts on his suit. Monday morning,
he goes to the post office. He's here
for his job.
>> [laughter]
>> It's very sad. I mean, I laugh, but it's
sad.
>> I'm laughing with him, not at him, sort
of.
>> [laughter]
>> And they're like, "Who are you?" He
said, "I'm I'm Bill. I'm here for my
job." They're like, "We don't know what
you're talking about." And he said,
"That damn Nixon, I'm going to get him."
Six months later,
Nixon comes to Steubenville to give a
speech.
Complete serendipity.
And Uncle Bill tries to get into the
civic center with a .45.
>> Oh, no.
>> And they get him.
And my mom said, I'll never forget these
words. She said, "There, but for the
grace of God, our name could have been
Oswald."
And then, how did Uncle Bill die? He got
hit by a train. And I said to my mom, I
was in college at the time. It was on
the front page of the paper.
I was like, "How do you not hear a train
coming?"
And she's like, "You know, this is one
of those things that's better just left
un- un-
unresolved."
>> Yeah, trains are really deadly, but
also,
if you don't go on the tracks, you have
a real good chance of
>> Yeah, maybe stay off the tracks,
especially when those arms come down and
the red lights are flashing.
You might want to stay off the tracks.
>> Indeed.
>> Have you heard the latest narrative
around the ex-CIA
I don't know what they call officers,
agents.
Uh, this is a new one I heard.
You guys, at first,
the CIA was like, "Oh, no.
They're telling all the secrets." But
now, people think, some people think
that the CIA is actually trying to help
you get on shows
>> Oh, we're friends again. Are we?
>> you can sow misinformation. So, now,
you're not a whistleblower anymore. Now,
you're a knowing and willing mouthpiece
of the agency.
>> Wow. And they came up with that all by
themselves?
>> Somebody did on the internet.
Bustamante's name was in there as well
and some a couple of other people I
didn't recognize their names as much.
But that's an interesting shift in
thought process.
>> I'll tell you there is literally nothing
that I hate more than when people say
once CIA, always CIA. Okay,
>> It's very movie based.
>> Yeah, I'm going to call Ed Snowden and
the sons of Philip Agee and Ray McGovern
and tell them that you think because of
your incredible [__] intellect that
they're still in the CIA and I'm in the
CIA. Well,
that was that prison sentence, that was
cover. They That was [laughter] That was
so you could establish cover. It's like
that is just great.
>> And then go on a podcast circuit so you
can just be the mouthpiece for the
agency.
>> Right.
>> Do you think the agency would get the
[__]
>> No, not anymore.
>> Do you think that they have people who
pay attention or
Sean Ryan posted a picture that he got
they he got an advertising request for
the agency. They wanted
>> kidding me?
>> I swear it was on his social media. It
was an ad by request from the agency.
I'm like, you should definitely
take that money.
>> Yeah.
>> And do the shittiest read.
>> It's terrible. I'll [laughter] tell you
just in the last 8 weeks, I mean on my
own podcast I've been doing a lot of,
you know, do you have gold in your IRA?
Go to johnlovesgold.com
or um running low on Ivermectin? All
Family Pharmacy/John
you get 10% off. And what are you going
to do?
>> So, lights don't pay for themselves.
>> Exactly. So, 8 weeks ago when things
started going nuts for me, all of a
sudden I'm getting calls from, you know,
Tom Ford eyeglasses and, you know, this
company and that company and a vineyard
in Napa. It's very cool. There was one I
turned down out of hand.
It was for a generic maker of Viagra.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay, no big deal. People take Viagra. I
don't, but maybe some people do.
But they wanted me to do this commercial
with an OnlyFans model.
And they wanted
>> more.
>> They wanted me to say, "Being with her
is not torture."
And I said,
>> Hold on, how much were they offering?
>> [laughter]
>> Don't actually say, I'm joking.
>> I SAID,
I SAID, "Am I a clown for you? That's
what you think this all boils down to.
I'm here for your amusement." Yeah.
>> To them it was a joke.
>> Yeah, it's all a big joke.
>> The moral stand that you took to them.
>> Yeah.
>> For clarity, I did do some funny ads for
Blue Chew dick pills because they gave
me full creative license and
I did like a 13-minute ad read one time.
I wove it into a story.
>> 13 minutes every
>> It was like the end of it was. It was
like, "Oh, and then an Amazon guy rung
the doorbell. He's like, 'Ding dong.'
I'm like, 'If your dong isn't being the
ding that you want it to be.'" It was
like,
>> [laughter]
>> That's awesome.
>> based in real life. It was the opening
of it. I just completely lost myself in
the story and I just left it in there.
That's a gift.
>> [laughter]
>> That's a gift. I will say,
this cashmere sweater is by Quince.
>> Yeah.
>> And Quince is one of my sponsors on John
Kiriakou's Dead Drop, which you can find
on Apple Podcasts. I'm proud to say, I
am in the top 1/10 of 1% of all of the 2
million podcasts on Apple Podcasts.
>> That's amazing.
>> It's fantastic. I don't know how it
happened. Um, in fact,
>> this this
>> getting your message out there and you
kept being yourself.
>> Thank you for that.
>> I mean, honestly, that's the answer to
it.
>> So, Quince reached out to me and said,
you know, we we want to give you $150 to
buy whatever you want on the Quince
uh webpage and then just be honest and
just talk for 60 seconds about about
what uh what you think about the
product. So, I go online. I I didn't
have this color of olive green.
This is the nicest
cashmere anything that I've ever owned.
Sometimes cashmere is very thin. There's
not much to it cuz it's so soft. This is
substantial. It's thick and it's the
softest thing I've ever owned. I wear it
all the time. And now I've gone back to
the Quince website with my own money and
spent another thousand bucks just
because I can't believe how high quality
this these clothes are.
>> Plus, when you think cashmere, you think
CIA officer.
>> Well, I'll tell you what.
>> You got to You need to have some other
little
>> patches.
>> That's only if you're an analyst.
>> A lot of cashmere around the world comes
from Pakistan. And so, when I was in
Pakistan, I'm getting, you know, emails
from everybody in my family. Like, "Can
you get me a cashmere sweater? Can you
get me a cashmere scarf?" So, I come
home with a suitcase full of just
cashmere to give away to people.
Well, I can't go to Pakistan and buy
cashmere. I got to pay, you know,
US prices. I'm happy to pay it if it's
this kind of quality.
>> Yeah. When brands reach out to me like
that, what I always do is I never take
their 150 or whatever it is. If it's a
brand that I'm interested in, I'll make
my initial purchase with my card. Just
cuz I want to be clean. And then I can
actually give them legit feedback. And
later on, if they want to enter into an
advertising relationship, I'll take your
money.
>> That is a very good idea.
>> It's like, "I'll take your money, but I
I'm going to enter into this like let me
let me be a paying customer first. Let
me get that experience." How is the last
eight weeks been when it just like Did
you just wake up one morning and you're
like, "I somehow I'm sitting on a rocket
ship"?
>> Quite literally. I happened to be in
Dubai
and and my niece called me from New
Hampshire and she says, "Uncle John,
you're blowing up on TikTok." I said,
"Why?"
And she said, "I don't know."
And then
one day later, I get a call from a major
global talent agency.
And the guy says, "Tell me you're not
represented."
And I said, "I'm not represented,
but I don't understand why this is
happening."
>> Mhm.
>> And then, a couple days after that, I
get a call from a reporter at Wired
magazine, and she wants to interview me
about my new
new found Tik Tok fame. I said,
"How did this start? I don't really
understand why it's happening."
>> upstream and actually figure out that
origin as well, too.
>> Well, she figured it out. It was Diary
of a CEO.
Which is funny, because
>> Well, first off, they could make his
facial expressions to some of your
answers are memes in and of themselves.
It's like, Steven, pick it pick the job,
just a little bit.
>> [laughter]
>> He was so much fun. First of all, he is
he's so incredibly bright
and had such insightful questions. It
wasn't just John telling stories. He had
he he posed questions that I had never
been asked to answer
>> Mhm.
>> before.
It was much more philosophical than a
normal, you know, John telling stories
kind of podcast.
Um but there was a kid, there's a
sophomore at the University of Texas
who took that interview and chopped it
up into shorts,
so that each short was a story. He gave
me an Alvin and the Chipmunks voice,
and then
the punchline would be in this ogre's
voice, you know, "And then I killed the
janitor." That kind of thing. And then
laser beams are shooting out of my eyes.
And, you know, for a second, I thought,
"Should I be offended? Offended that
they're like they're turning this into
something so lighthearted? I was talking
about serious issues here, torture."
This whole thing about hummus,
this was about a torture technique. And
then I thought, "No, I've got a sense of
humor, too. I'm going with it."
>> It'll lead more people to your actual
message, anyway.
>> And that's exactly what has happened.
>> Yeah.
>> And then I I was approached literally
the next day by Cameo.
Um it's an app where, you know, you can
commission D-list celebrities like me uh
to say happy birthday or, you know,
I have endorsed more kids for 11th grade
class president than you can shake a
stick at.
>> Do you have Do you end everyone with
remember the agency is always watching?
>> Sometimes I just go
>> [laughter]
>> If they only knew the truth.
>> But I got to say, it has been so much
fun. It has opened up doors for me that
I never imagined would ever open.
And I you know, I like to write books. I
I my ninth book is coming out in uh in
uh June. And
>> How do you enjoy the I just had a book
come out April 14th.
>> Congratulations.
It's hard work.
>> I was going to say, how did you possibly
enjoy that process enough to do it nine
times?
>> what it is? I stopped writing for other
people and started writing for myself.
>> That makes a lot of sense.
>> My first seven books were about the CIA.
And a whole bunch of them were
commissioned.
>> I read the first two. The first two was
Reluctant Spy: My Secret Life in the
CIA's War on Terror. Did really well,
made number five on the New York Times
bestseller's list. The second one was
Doing Time Like a Spy: How the CIA
Taught Me to Survive and Thrive in
Prison. And that one two literary
awards. I wrote it in longhand on on
legal pads at prison. And at the end of
each day of writing, because the guards
would tear them up and throw them in my
face, I would mail them back to my
attorney and mark them legal mail so
they couldn't intercept them.
>> yeah.
>> Um
>> The agency was definitely reading them
before you got them.
>> 100%
100%.
>> It would look like a It would look like
a clean envelope by the time it got to
your attorney, but they
>> Well, you know
>> There's going to be some eyes on those
things.
>> of people wrote back to me and said,
"Hey, your last letter was discreetly
slit on the side of the envelope." So, I
went down to the lieutenant's office one
guy one day and I said, "You guys, you
act like you're [__] geniuses and
you're not. You're dopes." I said,
"Listen, if you want to read what I have
to say, you don't have to slit the the
of the envelope open and then tape it up
like nobody's going to notice that. What
you do is you unfold a paperclip, you
put it in the top of the envelope so
that it hooks the paper, and then you
just turn the paperclip so that it's a
nice tight roll, and then you pull it
out, then you can read it, and then you
roll it back up and put it back in the
envelope. I said, "Seriously, I have to
explain it to you?"
>> Yeah. These These are rookie techniques.
You guys are trash. Rookie.
>> Day one [__]
>> But you know what? That reminds me of
something I wanted to tell you.
>> [laughter]
>> Something I wanted to tell you.
>> [snorts]
>> Saturday.
I'm driving. It's early in the morning.
I'm driving to George Washington
University. It was a day of TED Talks.
And I love TED Talks. I did one there
years ago. It was so much fun. So, I'm
going to the TED Talk. My phone rings.
And it's kind of early. It's like 8:00
or just before 9:00.
And it's a It's a number I didn't
recognize. So, I answer it.
And the guy says,
um
He gives me his name,
and he is a
He's the head of a Okay, I'll just say
it. So, he's the He's the director of
the Bureau of Prisons.
And I said, "Oh." I said, "To what do I
owe the pleasure of a call from the
director of the Bureau of Prisons?"
He says, "You have been talking [__]
about the Bureau of Prisons for 10
years." And I go, "Correction, I've been
talking [__] about the Bureau of Prisons
for 13 years. Get your number straight."
I know, buddy.
>> Yeah.
>> And he says, "Thus the reason for my
call." He said, "When you talk [__] you
always follow it up with a proposed
solution."
And I said, "Yeah." I said, "You're
corrupt, and your people are stupid, and
your entire
uh bureau is broken."
And he says,
"The president has mandated that I
completely
uh recreate the Bureau of Prisons.
I want to reorganize it. I want to
revamp it. And I want to know if you
would be willing to be a uh
a member of an advisory
committee.
>> I think we call that coming full circle.
>> I think so, too. I jumped at it. I said,
"Absolutely yes. When do you want to see
me?" He says, "Wednesday." I said,
"Done. I'll be there." And then he says,
"Can you recommend somebody who would be
really good?" And I said, "Absolutely
yes." I said, "He's got an Italian last
name that is going to be easily
recognizable,
but he did 17 years and he shouldn't
have done 17 days.
And how he's been able to maintain his
humanity, I have no idea.
I said, "He'll He'll set you straight."
>> Yeah.
Man.
What do you want to do
with
the notoriety as it builds? Like what
what are you looking at in your runway
in front of you? What do you want to do
with the attention? Having a platform is
an amazing thing.
>> It's amazing. I can't believe it.
>> Yeah.
>> Thanks for that question.
Um
a couple of things. Number one,
I've been talking about these same
issues
since 2007.
>> Yeah.
>> They're really, really important to me.
Human rights, civil rights, civil
liberties, transparency in government.
>> Do you think they're gaining traction?
>> I think so, too.
So, number one, I want to keep talking
to to increasingly large audiences.
Um
I really love writing.
I I love it. And I love that people
enjoy my books. I I love that people
enjoy hearing the stories. The stories
are all true,
which is why they've gained traction, I
think. So, I want to continue writing
for bigger and bigger audiences.
Since 2007, I've had a hobby where I
write television pilots. It's fun. And
I've been blessed since 2007 to have
sold eight of them in Hollywood. Yeah.
>> And so,
now I've got
I've got meetings scheduled over the
next two two three weeks with
household names.
>> Well, now that you have representation
>> And now I have representation.
>> [laughter]
>> I mean, these are like multiple Oscar
winners.
>> Oh, that's amazing.
>> Reaching out,
exchanging ideas,
I'm all in. I love it.
Uh and
you know,
I'm not ashamed to finally, for the
first time in my life,
make a couple of bucks.
I I I'm tired of being poor. I'm tired
of renting.
It's it's time to
it's time to ramp up my
my level of existence.
>> I don't think anybody out there is not
involved in that struggle, too.
>> Mhm.
>> Some of them talk about it a little bit
more than others, but yeah, everybody is
trying to make as much as they can in a
world that seems where the scarcity
model is approaching for everyone.
>> Yes.
Yeah, I'm tired of it.
>> Yeah, it's
man. People think
Yeah, let's just say don't join the
military. I mean, financial stability,
yes, for the 1st and the 15th, like your
check is going to come even if the
government shuts down.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> check may not be as big as you want it
to be.
>> Exactly. And you know, these [__]
Obama people, they confiscated my
pension
in 2012. So, I I've got nothing. I have
literally nothing.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, I've got to make that up now.
>> I think you're on a trajectory though
where you might look back at the number
of that pension.
>> Yeah.
>> And
even if they offered to you,
>> Yeah, maybe it's better that I don't
take it.
>> If you're in a If you're in a place
where it was offered to you,
I think the more powerful move
is to say [__] you.
>> Mhm. And your measly $3,000 a month.
>> You get I mean, it's one of the
misconceptions or the things that I
maybe not a misconception, but people
don't realize,
especially coming out of the world that
I was in in the military, this is all
I'm going to do, this is all that I can
do. And that's a very self-limiting
ideology.
>> Oh, you're exactly right. And then you
get out and if you can break yourself
from that ideology, the opportunities
that present themselves to you, you
would Of all the things I do now,
literally, people don't believe me. If
if you had given me an unlimited amount
of time in the years before I exited the
military, not a single thing that I do
now, the coffee shop, what? I didn't
even drink coffee till I was 27 years
old. That was seriously the best mocha
I've ever had in my life. When I took
the first sip, I was like, "Oh my god,
this is fantastic." It's Montana's, we
do a sprinkle of nothing there just to
get you coming back for the second one.
No, it wouldn't have been on there.
Hosting a podcast in the world I came
from, just like the world you came from,
they're like, "I'm sorry, I'm going to
willingly put myself on camera and put
my thoughts out on the internet to be
destroyed by by
>> See, you
you are exactly like I was where at the
agency, they a part of the culture is
that they convince you that your skills
are so specific that you can't do
anything else. For us, you move from the
agency into a defense contractor. For
you, you move into, you know, Blackwater
or some kind of contracting. And that's
just simply not true. You and I, when we
were walking over here,
I mentioned that first of all, God bless
Cameo. Seriously, I I actually, this is
how nuts it is.
For the last 8 weeks, I have set my
alarm every morning for 4:00 a.m.
>> [laughter]
>> Take it easy,
>> And I I answer Cameos from 7:00 and then
starting at 7:00, I do my normal day
because otherwise I can't catch up.
>> Yeah.
>> And I'm afraid of, you know, this all
just going away one day overnight, like
flipping a switch, like somebody flipped
a switch to start it in the first place.
So, my sister and I bought a laundromat.
And
now I won't be completely, you know,
poor.
>> Even if it does go away, this is what
I've realized in my life through the
technical term would be excessive amount
of failures that I have stumbled my way
through,
>> [laughter]
>> voluminous, if you will.
You figure out a way.
>> Yeah.
>> You do.
>> I I have I am finally at a place in my
life where I worry less about the
opportunities that are going to come
because I know that they will and I find
that I'm more receptive to them by just
kind of letting go of the reins a little
bit
and playing the field as it presents
itself to me instead of trying to mold
the chessboard into the which I've been
wrong
I've been wrong every time I've tried to
force the world into the chess moves
that I think are right.
>> Yeah, I mean it took me 48 years to
figure this out and for clarity I
haven't figured it out completely. Maybe
I'm just learning a little bit more from
my mistakes, but dude you're going to
figure it out. Even if it turns off
tomorrow
you're still going to figure it out cuz
you've put the volume of work in and
that I think is that's the difference
between
people who are truly suc- there are of
course blacks one events where somebody
will become instantaneously famous for
something. Good luck scaling that across
any generational level.
>> Look look at this a Huckleberry girl.
Like
>> Yeah, it didn't go too great for her.
>> No. She was a giant for like 2 weeks and
then
go on.
>> I don't know why anybody would take
advice from her financially. Like the
meme coin thing you didn't you really
thought that one was going to be like a
solid 401k investment strategy?
>> that's where you want to put your
hard-earned dollars.
>> Yeah. I mean life is self-critiquing in
many ways. It's like numchucks. If
you're not ready for them they're going
to break your nose.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah. That's exactly right.
>> You're going to it's you're going to
figure it out, man. The more work you
have put in it's the overnight 10-year
success. You're going to start getting
people now like oh must be nice, John.
Must be nice and it's like first off A
if you really want to piss them off say
it's actually nicer than you think it
could be.
>> [laughter]
>> And then it'd be
that twists them off a little bit. Like
you actually don't even have the
imagination to understand how nice it
is, but they're never going to see the
hard work. They're just going to see
that you have arrived at a place where
they want to be and they want to knock
it down a little bit.
>> Several friends of mine have told me
that
that they've never met anybody who works
as hard as I do. And
>> it's actually the key to success.
>> It is?
The hack culture that we live in, you
can hack a lot of things, but you can't
hack hard work.
>> You can't.
>> And I I don't sleep very much. I don't
really have any hobbies.
All I do is work.
>> Mhm.
>> Uh and it it this started off during
COVID. Well, I mean, I've always worked
hard, but especially during COVID, I had
a lot of trouble sleeping.
And I thought, well, I can lay here in
bed and stare at the ceiling, or I can
go downstairs and write an op-ed and
make $400. And so I started with the
op-eds. And then, oh, I started saying
most of my books, my first seven books
were about the CIA or something having
to do with the CIA. And then during
COVID, um
I thought, "No, you know what? I've ever
since I was a little boy, I've loved
cemeteries, exploring cemeteries. I love
the architecture. I love the symbolism
of the stones or what's on the stones,
but I especially love the fact that
literally everybody has a story. So, I'm
not talking about the most famous
people. I'm talking about interesting
people.
Um I was 9 years old. I told my mom one
day, we lived about a mile from the
cemetery, and I said, "I'm going to go
down to the cemetery and look for
salamanders."
So, I took a an empty shoe box. I went
down to the cemetery. I found a
salamander under a rock. I put him in
the box with some grass.
And when I got home, she said, "Did you
find any salamanders?" And I said,
"Yeah, I found one under a rock. It was
next to a gravestone that had a badge on
it." And she said, "What kind of badge?"
And I said, "It said Congressional Medal
of Honor."
And she said, "Oh, that's a hero. We
should go to the library and see what he
did." So, we went to the library, and we
we were regulars at the library anyway,
but we found that he was a farmer from
my hometown, and in the Battle of uh
Oh, shoot.
Battle of the Wilderness, was it?
Battle of Petersburg. He captured the
Confederate battle flag.
>> Damn.
>> And got the Congressional Medal of
Honor, came back home, farmed until
1878 and died.
And she said to me, I'll never forget
it. She said, you see
everybody has a story. You don't have to
be famous to have a story.
So, I've been to 73 countries and
probably 70 of those countries I've been
to a cemetery.
And I decided to write a cemetery book
about the cemeteries of Washington D.C.
So, I go online during COVID and I'm
looking and
it's there were like two dozen books
about Arlington National Cemetery.
And I learned that nobody had ever
written a book about the cemeteries of
Washington D.C.
>> Mhm.
>> There are fascinating people buried in
Washington.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I wrote the first book.
And it comes out in June and then I
followed it up. A funny thing is I sent
it to my publisher. It's Simon &
Schuster. And I said, look, I know you
guys don't normally publish books like
this, but this was important to me.
Could you take a look at it? And I told
him what it was, the editor. And he's
like, yeah, we don't really do books
like this, but
all right, I'll pass it around. He calls
me 2 weeks later and he says, this is
the best book you've ever written.
And they want to commission four more.
I said, oh, what do they want?
So, I finished, it's in editing now,
um,
Whispers in the Dirt, The Mafia Graves
of New York City.
>> Oh, damn.
>> I think that's going to be a good one.
And they want one on America's most
notorious serial killers, one on the
historic cemeteries of Chicago, and one
on the country western graves of
Nashville.
>> That's a real broad spectrum there.
>> Mhm.
>> I like the serial killers one.
>> I think so, too.
>> My wife is slightly disturbed by the
number of documentaries that I'll watch
about serial killers.
>> I'm addicted.
>> And she's like, what is it that you
>> She's like, what is it that you get out
of these? And I'm like, I'm not sure,
but I really can't turn it off.
>> Buddy, there was a serial killer in my
housing unit
uh, when I was in prison. We called him
Truck. He was a long-distance truck
driver. And in the days before DNA
testing, he would pick up prostitutes at
truck stops and have sex with them and
then strangle them, drive another hour,
and then just throw their bodies out of
the out of the truck. So,
he strangled a 16-year-old prostitute
and she survived. And she identified
him and the truck, and he was arrested.
He got 40 years.
For reasons that will never be clear to
me, he constantly sought my approval.
He started off like, "So, you were CIA?"
And I said, "Yeah." He goes, "I was CIA,
too. I was I used a shrimp boat to
smuggle
>> [laughter]
>> a shrimp" He specifically said a shrimp
boat to smuggle weapons to the Angolan
rebels. I go, "Get the [__] out of here.
A shrimp boat."
>> Forest Gump.
>> Yeah, exactly. A shrimp boat.
>> [laughter]
>> I go, "Get the [__] out of here." And
that just made him like seek my approval
more. He had these rotten nubs for
teeth.
>> Yeah.
>> So,
he would say stuff like, "Hey John, I
know that you like the Steelers and the
Steelers are are on TV this Sunday. I
saved you a seat in the in the TV room."
I'm like, "Okay, thanks, Truck."
"Hey John, I I know you like classic
rock.
There's a new classic rock station, 1600
AM." I'm like, "Thanks, Truck."
So, there was this other guy at the same
time we called Cat in the Hat cuz he had
this oddly elongated head. It was like a
birth defect. This crazy like you could
project a film on his on his forehead,
you know? And um
I had an empty bunk in my cell and
you have to get everybody's agreement to
move into somebody's cell. And we had a
rule in my cell, no pedophiles.
Pedophiles are banned.
So, I said to him, he wanted to move
into the bunk. I said, "You a
pedophile?" And he said, "No, I'm not a
pedophile." I said, "What's your What's
your crime?"
And he says, "Murder for hire." I said,
"I don't think I like that any more than
I like the pedophiles." I said, "What
were the circumstances of that crime?"
And he said, "I owed the mob a hundred
grand. I couldn't pay it, so I took out
a life insurance policy on my business
partner and I hired a hitman to kill him
and I got caught."
And I said, "Let me guess, you ratted
out the hitman."
He goes, "Well, it was either life
[laughter] in prison or 20 years." I
said, "No pedophiles, no rats."
So, we wouldn't let him in. Well, he was
mad.
One day
I hear my name on the
on the PA. Kyriacou, lieutenant's
office. Usually, that means you're going
to solitary. They didn't have the balls
to send me to solitary. So, it turned
out Jake Tapper wanted to interview me
and he had come up to the prison and I
had to sign a waiver and sit for the
interview.
So,
I'm sitting next to Truck later that
afternoon in the TV room. I am two feet
away from Cat in the Hat. He does not
seem to be sitting immediately directly
behind him. He's standing at the
computer. There's an internal email
system.
I'm sitting there. Truck is here. I'm
here. Cat in the Hat's here.
And he says, Cat in the Hat says to the
guy next to him, "Did you hear that
[__] Kyriacou? He got caught called
down to lieutenant's office. He goes,
'That guy's a [__] rat. He went down
there to rat us all out.'" And I just
sat there. Listen, if you call somebody
a rat, that's a big deal.
>> Oh, blood's going to be spilled.
>> Yeah.
>> I I didn't react in any way and Truck
says,
"That [__] guy just called you a
rat."
And I go,
"An hour ago, I heard him call you a
pedophile."
Of course, he didn't. I just made it up.
Without saying a single word,
Truck got up and beat this guy almost to
death.
>> And this is why, John, you were an
excellent case officer.
>> [laughter]
>> They had to land a helicopter in the
yard to life flight him to Pittsburgh.
Truck got 5 years added to his sentence.
Cat in the Hat was in intensive care for
like 6 weeks. He finally comes back to
the prison. He's all [__] up like, you
know.
>> Yeah.
>> And somebody had told him what had
happened. So, he comes up to me like
this and he goes,
"I I just wanted to say I'm sorry that I
called you a rat.
I should have never said that. I'll
never do it again." And I go, "Hey,
hey." I said, "Look at me."
I said, "So help me God,
if I ever hear my name cross your lips
ever again,
you're dead
and you're never going to see it
coming."
And nobody
messed with me.
>> I think we call those soft skills.
>> [laughter]
>> I got called down to the lieutenant's
office cuz I just continued watching the
Steelers game like this as as Truck is
beating him to death.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I get called down. They were like,
"What the [__] were you doing at that
fight?" I go, "What fight?"
>> Checking the score.
>> "The fight! You were sitting right next
TO THESE GUYS. THE GUY'S BEATING THE
OTHER GUY TO DEATH." I SAID, "I'm
watching the Steelers game. What are you
talking about?" "Oh, you're going to
tell us
that what we saw on four different
cameras didn't happen." I go, "Yeah,
maybe you were the ones fighting. Did
you ever think of that?" Admit nothing.
Deny everything. Counter accusations.
>> He's like, "GET THE [__] OUT OF MY
OFFICE."
SO.
>> Do you ever miss your old job?
>> Very much.
>> Yeah.
>> I can tell.
>> [laughter]
>> But so that's the thing though. Millions
of dollars spent on people, you can't
always put it all down. That stuff will
be with you for the rest of your life.
And again, they were looking for a
particular type of person that they can
hone and sharpen those skills in. I'll
tell you man, the the Italians adopted
me literally the day I arrived. And I
mean Italians named Gambino, Lucchese,
Genovese. These are serious guys. I I
loved them all. I saw two of them last
weekend. We had dinner together. They're
awesome.
And I said to one of them, I said, "This
[__] guy, Cat in the Hat, I said, I'm
taking this guy down."
And and a very senior guy in the Banana
family, he said, "Are you crazy?" He
said, "They're going to add years on
your sentence. You're going to end up
doing all of them solitary." And I said,
"I would never be so crude as to do it
with my own hands.
>> [laughter]
>> Who do you think I am?
>> Do you not know where I come from?
>> Oh my god, you think I don't think about
this stuff in advance?
>> Yeah.
There's a difference between brute force
>> That's right.
>> and
non-linear problem-solving.
>> In my second book, Doing Time Like a
Spy, I I start off with these 20 life
lessons that I learned at the CIA. And
one of them is let others do your dirty
work.
I would never do it myself.
>> Yeah.
>> Why would you? Why take the risk?
>> It's a good question. There There was
one uh
>> Good. I got to get you to the airport
here.
>> Oh yeah, I got to get you to the
airport.
>> We got time.
>> One of the Italian guys, he became my
best friend and is still one of my best
friends in the world. It's funny, you
know, you don't go to prison to make
friends.
But I made a friend in prison that
that he's like a brother, a brother to
me.
And um
we were talking about, you know,
having others do the dirty work. And he
said, he said, "That's some [__] up
kind of sociopath stuff right there."
And I said, "Yeah, okay, yes, you're
right. But the thing is,
if you want to stay safe
and you don't want to stay safe
in solitary,
you have to have others
do your dirty work."
And uh
it took him a little while, but he
understood. He mentioned to one of the
guards, he said to one of these guards,
"This was the the only guard that was
like universally reviled." He was the
only guard that wore a stab vest because
he was genuinely afraid somebody was was
to stab him.
>> Mhm.
>> And he And my buddy said, uh "Where are
you going to be?" uh They would do these
6-month rotations in different housing
units. "Oh, I'm going to be in Central
1." He said, "Oh, my buddy John's in
Central 1."
And um
the guard says, "The CIA guy, John?" And
he said, "Yeah."
And the guard says, "I never [__] with
that guy."
And my friend says, "Yeah? Why not?" And
he said, "That's all I need. I work 8
hours a day. I go out to my car and see
an standing out there. No, thank you."
>> [laughter]
>> I said, "Exactly."
>> Yeah, it's a deep pool.
Uh
last question for you. There are people
out there who view your old job
as their life's calling.
>> Mhm.
>> What would you say to a young person who
wants to have an impact in the
intelligence community
given the landscape of where I think we
both agree it is at right now. What
would you tell them?
>> I would give them the same advice that
my first deputy office director gave me.
He said, "You are going to see things
during the course of your career that
that's going to make your hair stand up.
Things that you cannot abide.
But understand that around year 10 of
your career, you're going to realize
that you're in a position of authority
all of a sudden. You're a branch chief,
a deputy group chief. If your career
really takes off, you're going to be a
group chief. And you can change those
things." He said, "There's always going
to be a CIA. There's nothing that
anybody can do to make it so that there
isn't a CIA anymore. And if you want to
change it, you have to change it from
the inside." He said, "Around year 10,
you can change it from the inside."
>> It's a bottoms-up approach as well.
>> Mhm.
>> I think that's the way.
>> I think so, too.
>> God, that's a tough journey, though.
>> And there are a lot of very bad people
in positions of authority right now.
>> Yeah.
I think there is more out there that are
good though.
>> That I agree with.
>> Yes, and that's why I still have hope.
There are good people out there.
You know, it's funny, too. There are a
lot of people
that just want to go work their day and
then go home, make dinner, and sit with
their family.
>> Yeah.
>> They don't even realize
that they're the kind of people that we
need to affect those changes.
>> Yeah.
>> Sometimes an opportunity presents itself
and you never saw it coming.
>> Agreed. What do you want to leave people
with?
Final thoughts.
>> You know, I've been the last eight or
nine weeks I've been able to connect
with Gen Z. And so my message is to Gen
Z. It is to tell the truth.
Because the truth really does set you
free.
There are some very contentious issues
that they're going to experience,
confront in their lifetimes. Be on the
right side of those issues. In the long
run, it's all worth it.
>> Couldn't agree more.
Hell yeah, John. Thank you for making
the trip out.
>> So good to see you. This is fun. Thanks
for the invitation.
>> Of course, man. My pleasure.